<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Review of the reflections on the Prince of Orange's declaration</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16015488</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16015488</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Review of the reflections on the Prince of Orange's declaration</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Churchil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:104765:1"/>
            <head>A REVIEW of the REFLECTIONS ON THE <hi>Prince of Orange's Declaration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Prince's unwillingneſs to charge the Government with any thing but what was Evident and Undeniable, affords the Reflection with which this Paper begins; That all the noiſe of a ſecret League with <hi>France</hi> has been only a feigned danger, and a falſe fear, ſince it is not ſo much as mentioned in the Prince's Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. It is certain, that the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour aſſerted it in a publick Audience, and in a Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial given in to the States General at the <hi>Hague;</hi> and all the World has clearly ſeen thro' the grimmace that the Court of <hi>England</hi> made upon it to Mr. <hi>Skel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> for it is not to be ſuppoſed, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> would have publiſhed this Alliance, unleſs it had been made, or that they would have made it, unleſs they had ſeen full powers for it in Mr. <hi>Skelton</hi>'s hands. But after all, as the Articles of it are ſecret, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Court of <hi>England</hi> having diſown'd it, the Princes exactneſs in not mentioning a doubtful thing, deſerved rather a Reflection in his favour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reflector is offended at the Prince's uſing the Stile of We and Us, for it ſeems <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee</hi> are ſo dear to him, that he cannot hear any thing out of that Cant. But tho' by the Connivance of our Court, <hi>France</hi> has robbed the Prince of his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, yet the Rights and Dignity of a Soveraign Prince remain ſtill with him, which will juſtify his ſpeaking in the plural number: And the other terms of Authority that are in his Declaration, being the uſual Stile of all that Command Armies, his uſing them imports no more, than that he is reſolved to uſe force for the Reſtoring of our Liberty; and if the Stile is a little high, it is their fault who would not hearken to ſofter and humbler repreſentations, and that had made it a Crime ſo much as to Petition.</p>
            <p n="3">3. There is nothing works more on weak people, than the faſtning an ill name even on the beſt actions, and therefore <hi>Invaſion</hi> being a term that naturally gives horrour, the Reflector faſtens that upon the Prince's Attempt to ſave the Nation; but things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear now too broad to be diſguiſed, and therefore the wiſe and worthy part of the Nation eſteems that to be a <hi>Deliverance,</hi> which is here called an <hi>Invaſion.</hi> It is true, the Prince promiſes to ſend back his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which imports, that he intends to ſtay behind; for he having engaged to ſee a Free Parliament Called and Aſſembled, muſt ſtay after his Army is ſent away, ſince no Parliament can be choſen with freedom, while the Nation is over-awed by a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Power; but when that is laid down of all hands, then the Prince will be obliged to ſee the promiſe that he has made to the Nation for a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment executed. So that all the malicious inſinuations of his Aſpiring to be King, which return ſo often in the Reflections, are thrown out only to create an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt jealouſie of His Highneſſes Intentions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſecurity which the Reflector promiſes to the Nation, and the Religion, by the Concurrence of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to ſave the Court, is now a little too late, the ſame Cheat will hardly paſs twice. This had once a great effect in bringing the Nation off from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Excluſion, and Men in the ſimplicity of their heart believed it. But the Court has taken ſo much pains to convince them of their errour, and has ſucceeded ſo effectually in it, that it is too great an impoſing upon us, to fancy that we can be ſo ſoon deluded again in the ſame manner. We know now, by ſad experience, what all the Promiſes and Oaths that a Papiſt can make to Proteſtants do ſignifie; and we ſee how little is to be built even on the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Prince, when a Jeſuit has the keeping of his Conſcience. Nor can it be any Reproach on our Religion, if the Nation comes under the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prince that has ſo near an intereſt in the Succeſſion to the Crown, to preſerve it ſelf and the Eſtabliſh'd Religion from the Conſpiracies of thoſe who intend to deſtroy both, and had made a great way in it, and would have probably brought their deſigns to a full ripeneſs this Winter, if the Prince's coming had not checkt them. The Reflector thinks the Prince ought to have turned his Arms rather on <hi>France,</hi> and allows that he has a juſt right to do it. But <hi>England</hi> had a greater Title to his Protection, and ought to have been firſt taken care of by him, and when that is once done, the propoſition here made, with relation to <hi>France,</hi> may be more ſeaſonable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Great exceptions are taken, becauſe the Prince founds the Invaſions that are made on the Proteſtant Religion, on this, that it is the Religion Eſtabliſh'd by Law; ſince our Reflecter tells us, that it is the Truth and not the Legality of a Religion that is its warrant; and that otherwiſe Paganiſm and Judaiſm had been ſtill the Eſtabliſht Religion. But the Reflector confounds things of different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If we conſider Religion, as it gives us a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the favour of God, and to Eternal happineſs, we ought to have no regard but to the truth of it. But when Religion is conſidered as the firſt of all Civil Rights, then the Legal Eſtabliſhment is the foundation of its Title: And if Legiſlators had not changed Laws, Paganiſm had been ſtill the Legal Religion, notwithſtanding its falſehood; and tho the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion is the only ground upon which we believe it, yet it muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Legal as well as it is true, before we can claim the Protection of the Law and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that has ſecured it to us; ſo that to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery, where that is the Eſtabliſht Religion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as certainly a Sin, as it is a debt that we owe our Religion and Country, to fight for the Proteſtant Religion, when the Law is for it, and illegal vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is imployed to pull it down.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Reflector's Common-place-ſtuff, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Diſpencing Power, has been ſo oft ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that it ſcarce deſerves a review. The Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of all Laws depends on the force of the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties againſt Tranſgreſſours; ſo that the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Penal Laws, carries in it the Diſpenſing with all Laws whatſoever; and by this Doctrine, the whole frame and ſecurity of our Government is at the King's diſcretion: Nor will that diſtinction of <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> and <hi>malum prohibitum</hi> ſave the matter,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104765:2"/>unleſs all the World were agreed upon the point; what things are evil of themſelves, and what not. In the ſenſe of a Papiſt, all the Laws againſt their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are ſo far from being Obligatory of their own Nature, that they are impious attempts upon that Authority which they think Infallible. Therefore all the diſtinction that is offered to ſave us from the exorbitancy of this Diſpenſing Power, as if it could not reach to things that are evil of themſelves, is of no force, unleſs a meaſure were laid down, in which both Proteſtants and Papiſts were agreed concerning things that are good or evil of themſelves. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Murther is allowed by all to be evil of it ſelf; yet if the Extirpation of Hereticks is a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on a Catholick King, as we are ſure it is, then a Commiſion given to deſtroy us would be a juſtifiable Action, and ſo the Laws againſt Murder and Manſlaughter might in that caſe be Diſpenſed with, ſince the killing of Hereticks is by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Papiſts only <hi>Malum prohibitum,</hi> and not <hi>Malum in ſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Our Authour might have ſpar'd his Rhetorick how well ſoever he loads it upon the head of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and Liberty of Conſcience, if it had been but for this reaſon, that it diſcover'd too plainly who it was that wrote theſe Reflections, which perhaps he may have e're long ſome Reaſons to wiſh it were not ſo well known, as he has taken pains to do by his luxuriant Stile. All that can be ſaid on this head, belongs very pertinently to the conſideration of a Parliament, but is very improperly urged in favour of the bloodieſt of all Perſecutors, who could not begin their breaking in upon our Laws and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion more dextrouſly than at this of Liberty of Conſcience, tho' they themſelves had been the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of all the ſeverities that had been acted among us, and intended by this ſhew of eaſe to bring us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the Cruelties of an Inquiſition, which is one of the inſeparable Perquiſities of that bloody Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The greateſt part of the Invaſions made on our Government, that are ſet forth in the Princes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, are acknowledged to be ſuch by our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector. But he thinks they are now redreſſed. The High Commiſſion is at an and, <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is reſtor'd. If the King had of his own mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and from a ſenſe of the juſtice of the thing done all this while he apprehended no danger, and if he had brought the Authors of thoſe Pernicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils to condign Puniſhment, then it had been more reaſonable to Value thoſe Acts of Juſtice, by which the former Violences had been in ſome meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired: but what is done in the preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſhews only a meanneſs of Spirit, and a feebleneſs in the Government: And ſome Mens Tempers are too well known, to ſuffer us once to doubt of their returning back to all their former Violences, and of their carrying them on to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Exceſſes; if God for the ſins of the Nation, ſhould blaſt this Glorious Undertaking. And if the Charters are now reſtor'd, we know by the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the late Regulators of Corporations, that it was far from their thoughts but a little while ago, ſo that this is likewiſe an effect of the preſent Fear they are under; and it ſhews that after all their Huffings during their Proſperity, they ſink under dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers as much as others, whoſe Memory they are ſo careful to blemiſh, how much ſoever they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to them. It is here ſaid, that moſt of the Charters were taken away in the late King's time: But as it is well known under whoſe Influence the laſt years of the late Reign were conducted, ſo the limiting the Elections to a ſpecial number, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Cuſtom and Preſcription, was the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the preſent Reign.</p>
            <p n="9">9. But if the Reflector will not juſtifie every thing that the Government has done, and thinks the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate of things could hardly bear ſo groſs an Abuſe; yet he inſiſts often upon this, that theſe Illegal things were fit for the Conſideration and the Redreſs of a Parliament, and that they do not juſtific the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Attempt. But the Prince's Deſign is only to ſee a Free Parliament Choſen and Aſſembled according to Law. For our Author and his Complices (for he reckons himſelf in the Miniſtry, <hi>Sect.</hi> 23. when he names the things objected againſt the Miniſtry, as objected <hi>againſt us,</hi>) had taken ſuch care to keep off a parliament, and to overturn all Corporations, to Corrupt all Elections, and to provide for falſe Returns by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Sheriffs and Mayors, that we were out of all hopes, or rather out of a poſſibility of ever ſeeing a Free Parliament again; ſo that any nearer Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that we now have of one, is wholly owing to the Prince's Undertaking; and indeed what is given us at preſent, is done with ſo ill a Grace, and the Popiſh and corrupt Miniſtry, is ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and cheriſhed with ſo particular a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that they ſeem to have a mind to make the Nation ſee that all is done ſo groſly, that thoſe who are cheated by it, will have no excuſe for their Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſince the Trick is acted with too bare a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to paſs on any.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Reflector thinks that the Prince ought to have complained to the King of theſe Abu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, tho' in other places of this Paper, he pretends that the Prince was not a proper Judge in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; he Aggravates the Prince's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> an Uncle and a Father-in-Law without warning giv'n. Indeed, if this were the Caſe, all that could be ſaid upon it, was, that he had copied from the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern that was ſet him in 1672. in that famous At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>na</hi> Fleet: What Complaints the Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>de, or what encouragement he had to make any, and how they were entertain'd and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, are Domeſtick matters, of which the World knows little, ſince all that has appear'd in publick was in Mr. <hi>Fagel's</hi> Letter, and how well that was received, and how civilly it was anſwer'd, all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſaw. It is true, the Prince is very nearly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the King, but there are other Ties ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than the Bonds of Fleſh and Blood; He owes more to the Proteſtant Religion and to the Nation, than can be defaced by any other Relation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and if the failing in one Relation excuſes the other, then enough might be ſaid, to ſhew at what pains the Court of <hi>England</hi> has been, to free the Prince from all other Engagements, except thoſe of <hi>Loving Enemies,</hi> and doing good to thoſe who <hi>Deſpitefully uſe us,</hi> for upon this account the Prince lies under all poſſible Obligations.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Reflector thinks, that thoſe who left <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> were driven by a needleſs fear; but tho' he has no reaſon to apprehend much from the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, yet thoſe who ſaw the laſt Bloody <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> may be forgiv'n, if they have no mind to ſee ſuch another. He faintly blames that great Change that was lately made in the whole Government of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104765:2"/>but he preſently excuſes it, ſince it was Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural for the King and his Friends to deſire to be ſafe ſome where; till they had fair Quarter in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> they muſt make ſure of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but he adds, that as ſoon as that was done, the thing muſt have returned into its old Channel again. This ought to be writ only to <hi>Iriſh-</hi> men, for none of a higher ſize of Underſtanding can bear it; if it can ever be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Papiſts have yielded up any thing, which they had once wrung out of the hands of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, except when they were forced to it; we may believe this and all the other groſs things which are here impoſed on us. The plain caſe was, the Papiſts reſolved to deſtroy us, and to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in caſe to do it as ſoon as was poſſible; ſo they went about it immediately in <hi>Ireland,</hi> only they have delay'd the giving the Signal for a new <hi>Maſſacre,</hi> till matters were ripe for it in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 The Reflector has reaſon to avoid the ſaying any thing to the Article of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for even his Confidence could not ſupport him in juſtifying the King's claiming an Abſolute Power, to which all are bound to obey without reſerve, and the Repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a great many Laws upon that pretenſion; this is too groſs for Human Nature, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of all Religions whatſoever. Our Author a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voids ſpeaking to it, becauſe he does not know the extent of the Prerogative of that Crown. But no Prerogative can go to an Obedience without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, nor can Abſolute Power conſiſt with any Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Government.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Declaration had ſet forth, that the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Counſellors had repreſented the Expedient, offer'd by the Prince and Princeſs, as offer'd on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to diſturb the Quiet and Happineſs of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; upon which the Reflector beſtows this kind Remark on the Miniſtry: And did they not ſay true, as it happens? Believe me, ſome Folks think many of them are not often guilty of ſuch foreſight: The Writer is angry that his ſide is not uppermoſt, and tho' he includes himſelf in the Miniſtry by ſaying Us, when he ſpeaks of them, yet here, tho' he was to cenſure the Party that is againſt him, he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes them, by ſaying many of the Counſellors uſe not to have ſuch foreſight: But perhaps they can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as much to his foreſight, and with as much reaſon. But if the King comes up to Mr. <hi>Fagel</hi>'s Letter, why was it rejected with ſo much ſcorn, and anſwered with ſo much Inſolence? Now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they would hearken to it, when they have brought both themſelves and the Nation to the brink of Ruine, by their mad Councils: But they ought to be forgiven, ſince they have been true to the Principles and Dictates of their Religion.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Our Reflector thinks a Free Parliament a <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera,</hi> and indeed he and his Friends have been at a great deal of pains to render it impoſſible. But perhaps he may be quickly cured of his Error, and a Free One is the ſooner like to be choſen, when he and ſuch as he, are ſet at a due diſtance from the publick Councils. If Members are ſometimes choſen by drinking and other Practices, this is bad enough, but ſtill it is not ſo bad as the laying a force upon the Electors, and a reſtraint upon the Election. Nor is it very much to the King's Honour, to remember how the laſt Parliament was choſen; it was indeed a very diſguſting Eſſay in the beginning of a Reign, and gave a ſad proſpect of what might be look't for; but if one Violence was born with, when the ſtruggle of another Party ſeemed to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe it; this does not prove that a courſe of ſuch Violences, when the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is become both more viſible, and leſs excuſable, ought to be endured. If the Members of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament proved Worthy Patriots, I do not ſee why they ought not to be remembred with Honour, tho' there is a great deal to be ſaid upon their firſt ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to that Character, which they maintained indeed nobly; ſo that if the firſt Conception of that Parliament was Irregular, yet its End was Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, ſince never a Parliament was diſſolv'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a more Glorious Account.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The Reflector ſets up all his Sail, when he enters upon the Article of the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> This was a Point by which he hoped to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit highly, and upon that, to gain ground on that Party of the Court, on whom he had reflected with ſo much ſcorn. Therefore here muſt the Prince be attackt with all the Malicious force to which his Rhetorick could carry him; and all thoſe Men of Honour that went over to wait on him at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and to repreſent to him the bleeding and deſperate Condition of the Nation, muſt be ſtigmatized as a lewd Crew of Renegadoes; tho' I muſt tell him, that the common acception of Renegadoe, is one that changes his Religion, and by this he will find ſome near him to whom that Character belongs more juſtly. He almoſt blames the King for the low ſtep he lately made to prove that Birth: It was a low one indeed, to make ſo much adoe, and to bring together ſuch a Solemn Appearance, to hear ſo ſlight a Proof produced: which could have no other effect, but to make the Impoſture ſo much the more viſible, when the utmoſt attempts to ſupport it, appear to be now ſo feeble, that as to the main point of the Queen's bearing the Child, there is not ſo much as a colony of a proof produc'd: And it is certain, that if this had been a fair thing, the Court would have ſo managed it, that it ſhould not have been in the power of any Mortal to have called it in queſtion: And on the other hand, they have ſo managed it, that one muſt needs ſee, in every ſtep of it, broad marks of an Impoſture. It will not be half Proofs, nor Suborned Witneſſes, that will ſatisfie the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſo great a Point. But I will enter into no particulars relating to this Buſineſs, which will be better laid open when a Free Parliament meets to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine it.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Reflector charges upon the Prince all the miſeries that may follow on a War, as an unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble return to the kindneſs that the Nation has ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. But if the diſſolution of the Government, brought on by the Court, has given a juſt riſe to his coming, then the ill effects that may fall out in the progreſs of his deſign, are no more to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on him, than the miſeries to which a ſevere Cure of the ill effects of a wilful diſorder expoſe a Patient, ought to be imputed to a Phyſician, that betrays his Patient if he ſlatters him; and that muſt apply violent Remedies to obſtinate Diſtempers. I do not hear from other hands, that the Lords and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops about the City have diſowned their inviting the Prince: and I do not believe it the better, becauſe our Author affirms it. But if it were true, there are others in <hi>England</hi> beſides thoſe about the City: ſo the thing may be true, tho' a few about the City had not been in it. A ſmall Civility is beſtowed on the Prince, when it is ſaid, that he would not have affirmed it, if he did not believe it; but this is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104765:3"/>ſoon taken off, and it is ſaid, that doubtleſs he was abuſed in this. If this is to be ſuppoſed, the Prince is as weak a man, as his Enemies, for their own ſakes, ought to wiſh to be; if he could ſuffer himſelf to be engaged in a matter of this nature, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſured of the grounds he went on.</p>
            <p n="17">17. What is ſaid of the Prince's referring all matters to the determination of a Free Parliament, is too flat to require an Anſwer: This was a plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible thing, and therefore it ought to have been ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite paſt over, or ſomewhat of force ought to have been ſet againſt it. This is not the refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of other peoples Rights to a Parliament; but the leaving the healing of the Nation to thoſe who are its proper Phyſicians. And the taking a Cure out of the hands of the Court, inſtead of that, is like the renouncing a ſure Method and a good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ian, and the hearkening to the arrogant promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a bold Mountebank. The Prince has promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſend away his Army as ſoon as the ſtate of the Nation will permit, upon which the Reflector ſays, that here is but a Foreigner's word againſt our own King's; and he refers it to our Allegiance to judge, which of the two we ought to truſt. But I cannot find out in what the Prince's promiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts any that the King has made; for I do not hear that the King had promiſed that theſe Troops ſhall not return; and unleſs that were the Caſe, I cannot find out the Contradiction; and after all, if we muſt ſpeak out, there is ſome odds to be made between a Prince whoſe Religion, as well as his Honour, has ever determined him to keep all his Promiſes, and another whoſe Religion has taught him ſo often to make bold with all his.</p>
            <p n="18">18. The Prince's ſummoning the Nobility and Gentry, as it is the uſual ſtile of all Generals, ſo it requires them only to appear and to act for their Country and their Religion; and his promiſing to have a Parliament called in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports no more but that he is come with a Reſolution to have the Government ſetled on its true Baſis, and that he will ſee it done.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Reflector is in great wrath, becauſe the Prince has, in his Additional Declaration, ſhewed how little regard ought to be had to that imperfect Redreſs of Grievances that has been offered of late. But it had been a concurring in the Cheat, to ſuffer it to paſs, without laying it open: When fair things are offered from men to whom we ought to truſt, it is as reaſonable to receive them, as it is to reject all deceitful things, when the Truth is apparent. Therefore as the Prince had no reaſon to abandon the Cure of the Nation, after the ſteps that he had made, becauſe of the endeavours of the Court to lay it aſleep; ſo he has ſo purged himſelf from the Imputations of deſigning a Conqueſt, that all out Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector's malice cannot make them ſtick; and all that Noble Company that came over with him, and that have ſince come in to him, are a proof of this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond exception: Let all Men of Sence judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Army compoſed of ſo many <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, or another made up of ſo many Noblemen and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of great Families and Eſtates, are likelieſt to ſet about the Conquering the Nation.</p>
            <p n="20">20. He ſaucies that what the Prince gets by the Sword, he will keep by the Sword: And upon this he tells us, that he ſaid Once to the King, that the bringing the <hi>Dutch</hi> Army to the Diſcipline in which it was, had coſt 1300 Lives: upon which he wiſhes thoſe who value the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and Trials by Juries, to make ſome Reflections. But ſince the Situation and Conſtitution of <hi>Holland,</hi> makes an Army neceſſary to them, and ſince they have provided by particular Laws, that Marſhal Diſcipline ſhould be Maintain'd by a Council of War, nothing could have been contriv'd more for the Prince's Honour, than to tell us that he has ſo ordered the Matter, that the Army is become one of the moſt Regular and Inoffenſive Bodies of Men that is in all <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> which this Nation ſees now, with no ſmall aſtoniſhment; to whom one Regiment of <hi>Iriſh,</hi> has given more fear and diſorder, than this great Army has done to the places thro' which it has paſs'd. The Reflector tells us alſo, as a very ridiculous thing, that the Prince who has left the <hi>Dutch</hi> no Liberty at home, comes now to ſecure ours here: And to make the Parallel compleat between the Prince and a near Relation of his, he pretends that he broke his Oath to the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> he having promiſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be <hi>Statholder,</hi> tho' it ſhould be offer'd him: And to conclude all againſt him, he ſaies, there is no more proportion between the Ancient Liberties of <hi>Holland,</hi> and his preſent Government, than there is between <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Brandford.</hi> Here is the force of all his Malice, but we who have ſeen the State of Affairs in <hi>Holland,</hi> and the Freedome of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there, know that <hi>England</hi> can wiſh for no greater Happineſs, than that the Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here, may be Maintained as exactly here, as they are there: And the late Unanimous Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all the Provinces, and of all the Negatives in every Province, and not only of all the Members in every one of theſe Bodies, but indeed of the whole People all over the Provinces, <hi>Amſterdam</hi> it ſelf leading the way to all the reſt, by which they gave their Fleet, their Army, and their Treaſure ſo frankly up to the Prince, was an evidence of his good Government, beyond all that can be ſet forth in words: For real Arguments conclude alwaies truly. And for the Prince's Oath, it was an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to the States, and was intended even by thoſe who framed it, only to hinder all Caballing for obtaining any ſuch offer to be made him. But when they were brought to that extremity, to which we helped to drive them, ſo that there was a change made in the greateſt part of the whole Government, they Unanimouſly found the neceſſity of Veſting the Prince with the full Authority of <hi>Statholder;</hi> and therefore the Oath being made to them, it was in their Power to give it up: So that here was no breach of Oath, but only a Relaxation of the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation that was made to the States. The Reflections end with a piece of Railery, which might paſs, if it were either witty or decent; but if the things that are objected ſeem irregular, I fancy that Mr. <hi>Pen</hi>'s Writing for Popery, and Mr. <hi>Stewart</hi>'s for Tyranny, are things every whit as Incongruous as any of theſe, with which the Reflector diverts himſelf.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>William Churchil,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
